<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document order="1">
<properties>
	<title>Get involved</title>
</properties>

<body>

<intro>
<p>
Open source project is made of contributions. Anyone can
get involved by submitting patches to the code, documentation
or anything else. Reporting bugs and explaining with a good level 
of detail how to reproduce it is extremelly important.
</p>

<p>
If you not familiar with patches, see <a href="patch.html">Creating and sending a patch</a> document.
</p>

<p>
Just like The Apache Software Foundation, we are also under the philosophy of Meritocracy:
</p>

<p>
<blockquote>
<i>
The roles and responsibilities that people can assume in the project are 
based on merit. Everybody can help no matter what their role. Those who 
have been long term or valuable contributors to the project obtain the 
right to vote and commit directly to the source repository.
</i>
</blockquote>
</p>

<p>
After a demonstration of committment, good technical skills and more important
good judgment, you may be invited to join the project as a committer.
This happens after someone at the PMC proposes your name and a vote is started.
After the majority of PMC member cast their votes and there are no vetoes, 
an invitation is sent.
</p>

<p>
There are no recipes to join the project. Just subcribe to the mailing list
and participate with opinions, patches and reviews.
</p>

</intro>

<section>
<title>Where</title>

<p>
Castle development discussion 
takes place on the 
<a href="mailinglists.html">devel mailing list</a>.
You do not need to subscribe to the list just to submit a patch or two, 
but if you want to be involved with Castle development on a regular basis, 
you should probably subscribe. It is high-traffic, but threading tends to be 
fairly disciplined, so you can ignore conversations you are not interested in. 
</p>

<p>
For real-time chat, developers use the same IRC channel as everyone else: 
irc.freenode.net/##castleproject.
</p>

</section>

<section id="seealso">
	<title>See also</title>
	
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li><a href="../subversion.html">Castle Subversion Repository</a></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	
</section>

</body>
</document>
