<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document order="30">
  <properties>
    <title>Creating and sending a patch</title>
  </properties>
<body>

<intro>

<p>
A patch is a file that uniffies the differences of a target file. 
It is useful to us as we can see exactly what you changed, think 
about the implications and ultimately approve the patch so your 
changes are committed to the code repository.
</p>

<p>
We strongly encourage that you include test cases for your changes.
If you need any help on how to test something, ask for help
on the development mailing list.
</p>

</intro>

<section>
	<title>Creating a patch with TortoiseSVN</title>

	<p>
	After you have finished changing the files you are
	ready to create a patch file. To do so, right
	click the files or the root folder 
	and select TortoiseSVN\Create Patch
	</p>

	<note>
	<p>
	If you don't create the patch from the root folder - then please include the path
	of the files you are supplying the patch for. Castle contains a lot of projects with 
	a lot of files, telling a maintainer where to apply your patch makes their lives easier 
	and also makes it more likely that your patch will be applied quickly. e.g. "ViewComponent.patch"
	"Here's a patch for \MonoRail\Castle.MonoRail.Framework\ViewComponent.cs"
	</p>
	</note>


	<note>
	<p>
	If your modification includes new files or new folders
	you must <b>add</b> them before create the patch.
	When you <b>add</b> the files you show mark the files
	for inclusion. To add files or folders with TortoiseSVN, right click
	the folder or the files and select TortoiseSVN\Add.
	</p>
	</note>
	
	<p>
	<img relative="images/community/patchingwithtortoise.png"/>
	</p>
	
	<p>
	A patch file looks like the following:
	</p>
	
	<pre format="html"><![CDATA[
Index: navigation.xml
===================================================================
--- navigation.xml	(revision 2776)
+++ navigation.xml	(working copy)
@@ -1,6 +1,6 @@
 <?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
 <project>
-<localimage>images/activerecord-med.png</localimage>
+<localimage>images/ar_rawlogo.gif</localimage>
 <title>ActiveRecord</title>
 <body>
 <group type="light">
	]]></pre>
	
	<p>
	It shows the lines removed (-) and the lines included (+)
	</p>
	
	<p>
	After creating the patch you can submit it 
	using <a href="../jira.html">our issue tracker</a>
	or sending as an attachment to our development mailing list.
	</p>
	
</section>

</body>
</document>
