<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document order="30">
  <properties>
    <title>Handlers</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<intro>

<p>
Each component registered on the MicroKernel has a
respective handler instance (which is a class that implements <tt>IHandler</tt>).
The handle is a kind of gate keeper for the component. The handle's roles are:

<ul>
<li>Create the ComponentActivator instance</li>
<li>Create the LifestyleManager instance</li>
<li>Ensure that the minimal set of dependencies required by the components can be reached</li>
</ul>
</p>


<p>
The last bullet is the more complex one. The MicroKernel was designed to be dynamic
which means that components can be registered and removed at any time. Others IoC 
containers are static, which greatly simplify their implementation but are not as powerful
as dynamic ones.
</p>

<p>
The the MicroKernel uses a dynamic approach, the handler check if the current 
state of the container have all others components/services and configuration
required by the component it is keeping. If not, the handler subscribes 
to a container event so it will know when a new component is registered. Each component
later registered will trigger a check and the handler will re-evaluate its state.
</p>

<p>
While the minimal set of dependencies cannot be reached, the handle is said to be 
in a <tt>WaitingDependency</tt> state. If you try to request a component whose handler
is in this state, an exception will be thrown. The exception message will list 
what the handler is waiting for.
</p>

<p>
The most complex situation is when the component dependencies are registered but 
the dependencies themselves are in the <tt>WaitingDependency</tt> state. Trying to 
request this component will also throw an exception. The exception message will tell
you that a component the handler waits for was registered, but is not in a valid state.
</p>

<p>
<img relative="images/container/microkernel_handler.png" />
</p>


<p>
You should also consult the <a href="mktypedocs/Generated_IHandler.html">IHandler API document</a>.
</p>

</intro>

</body>

</document>
