<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
<properties>
	<title>How Castle Anakia works</title>
</properties>

<body>

<intro>
<p>
The sections below gives an overall explanation of the inner working of Castle Anakia.
</p>

</intro>

<section id="theprocess">
<title>The process</title>
<p>
The NAnt task runs against a content folder, recursively. An object model is constructed 
and populated to reflect that structure. See the figure below.
</p>

<p>
<img relative="images/others/anakia/anakia-object-model.png"/>
</p>

<p>
Each physical folder will be represented by a <tt>Folder</tt> instance. A <tt>Folder</tt>
holds a collection of <tt>DocumentNode</tt>s. Each <tt>DocumentNode</tt> has a type:
</p>

<p>
<ul>
<li><tt>Index</tt>: used for <i>index.xml</i> files</li>
<li><tt>Navigation</tt>: used for <i>navigation.xml</i> files</li>
<li><tt>Ordinary</tt>: used for all other xml files in the folder</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>
A set of visitors transverse the object model to create the site map, breadcrumbs and finally 
the html files.
</p>

</section>

<section id="thetransformation">
<title>The transformation</title>
<p>
The transformation of the xml content is handled by a NVelocity template. The following context
entries are made available to the template:
</p>

<p>

<table style="border: solid 1px black;" border="1" width="60%" bordercolor="gray" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0">
<tr>
<td>Context entry name</td>
<td>Description</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>breadcrumbs</td>
<td>List of <tt>BreadCrumb</tt> instances. Each <tt>BreadCrumb</tt> has a <tt>Title</tt> and a <tt>Relative</tt> property that allow you to generate the links</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>meta</td>
<td>Instance of <tt>DocumentMeta</tt> which is created for each document content based on the <tt>properties</tt> node</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>root</td>
<td>The <tt>XmlElement</tt> for the current content file</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>node</td>
<td>The <tt>DocumentNode</tt> instance for the content file</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>sitemap</td>
<td>A <tt>XmlElement</tt> for the generated sitemap</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>project</td>
<td>A <tt>XmlElement</tt> for the <tt>project.xml</tt></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>folder</td>
<td>The <tt>Folder</tt> instance</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>converter</td>
<td>An instance of <tt>SimpleConverter</tt> that is able to convert strings to different types</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>helper</td>
<td>An instance of <tt>SimpleHelper</tt></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>navigation</td>
<td>A <tt>XmlElement</tt> with the content of <tt>navigation.xml</tt></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>relativePath</td>
<td>The relative path to access the root folder.</td>
</tr>
</table>

</p>

</section>


</body>
</document>
