<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document order="1">
  <properties>
    <title>Configuration and Initialization</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

<intro>
<p>
Before using an ActiveRecord class in runtime you must properly initialize
the framework. This must happen only once for the entire application lifetime.
</p>

<p>
In order to initialize the framework, you must supply some obligatory information.

<ul>
<li>What kind of database you are using</li>
<li>How to connect to it</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>
Optionally you can turn debug on, turn on caching and make fine tune adjustments.
The sections below explain how to start the framework and give it all information it 
needs to initialize itself properly.
</p>

<download relative="!download/activerecord/trunk/InitializingAndConfiguring.zip" filename="InitializingAndConfiguring.zip">

</download>

</intro>

<section id="Initializing">
	<title>Initializing</title>
	
	<p>
	Before using ActiveRecord your application must invoke
	the method <tt>Initialize</tt> on <tt>ActiveRecordStarter</tt>.
	This method has a few overloads. Ultimately it needs an implementation
	of <tt>IConfigurationSource</tt> and a set of ActiveRecord types to inspect.
	It basically configures NHibernate, inspects the types 
	for semantic errors and constructs the mapping for each of them.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	In this section we will postpone the construction or 
	obtention of an <tt>IConfigurationSource</tt>
	and focus the attention on the overloads. 
	</p>
	
	<section>
		<title>Initialize(IConfigurationSource source, params Type[] types)</title>
	
		<p>
		This overload allow you to specify an <tt>IConfigurationSource</tt> and an array
		of ActiveRecord types. For example:
		</p>
		
<pre format="cs">
using Castle.ActiveRecord;

IConfigurationSource config = ... ;

ActiveRecordStarter.Initialize(config, typeof(Blog), typeof(Post));
</pre>
		
		<note>
		<p>
		When you use this overload you must remember that once you add one or more
		ActiveRecord types you must include the types on the call, otherwise the new
		types will not work.
		</p>
		</note>
	
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Initialize(Assembly assembly, IConfigurationSource source)</title>
	
		<p>
		This overload allow you to specify an <tt>IConfigurationSource</tt> and an 
		<tt>Assembly</tt> instance. ActiveRecord then iterates over all types on the 
		<tt>Assembly</tt> and initializes the types it identifies as ActiveRecord types.
		The implementation checks whether the type uses the <tt>ActiveRecordAttribute</tt>.
		</p>
		
		<p>
		Using this overload saves you from updating the call everytime a new type is 
		included to your domain model.
		</p>
		
		<p>
 		Example:
		</p>
		
<pre format="cs">
using Castle.ActiveRecord;

IConfigurationSource config = ... ;

Assembly asm = Assembly.Load("Company.Project.Models")

ActiveRecordStarter.Initialize(asm, config);
</pre>
		
		<warning>
		<p>
		Try to create an <tt>Assembly</tt> exclusively for ActiveRecord 
		types if you can. This overload will inspect all public types. If there are
		thousands of types, this can take a considerable amount of time.
		</p>
		</warning>
	
	</section>
	
	
	<section>
		<title>Initialize(Assembly[] assemblies, IConfigurationSource source)</title>
	
		<p>
		Just like the overload above, this overload allow you to specify an <tt>IConfigurationSource</tt> and an array of <tt>Assembly</tt> instances. 
		ActiveRecord then iterates over all types on the 
		<tt>Assembly</tt> array and initializes the types it identifies as ActiveRecord types.
		The implementation checks whether the type uses the <tt>ActiveRecordAttribute</tt>.
		</p>

		<p>
 		This overload is useful when you have reusable ActiveRecord classes and a project
		uses a combination of reusable classes and their own types.
		</p>
		
		<p>
 		Example:
		</p>
		
<pre format="cs">
using Castle.ActiveRecord;

IConfigurationSource config = ... ;

Assembly asm1 = Assembly.Load("Company.Common.Models")
Assembly asm2 = Assembly.Load("Company.Project.Models")

ActiveRecordStarter.Initialize(new Assembly[] { asm1, asm2 }, config);
</pre>
	
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Initialize()</title>
	
		<p>
		This overload uses an assumption to initialize the framework. 
		It assumes that 
		<ul>
			<li>
			The configuration can be obtained from the 
			configuration associated with the AppDomain (more on that on the next section)
			</li>
			<li>
			All ActiveRecord types can be found on the executing assembly.
			</li>
		</ul>
		</p>

		<p>
 		As much as this is the simpler overload, it is also the one which imposes
		more restrictions. As a general rule, do not use it.
		</p>
		
<pre format="cs">
using Castle.ActiveRecord;

ActiveRecordStarter.Initialize();
</pre>
	
	</section>
	
</section>

<section id="configuring">
	<title>Configuring</title>

	<p>
	Configuring Castle ActiveRecord is necessary as it will never be
	able to guess the database you are using or the connection string.
	When you configure it, you end up configuring the NHibernate instance 
	ActiveRecord uses, and some other configuration is specific to ActiveRecord.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	Basically you need to tell:
	
	<ul>
	<li>The driver</li>
	<li>The dialect</li>
	<li>The connection provider</li>
	<li>The connection string</li>
	</ul>	
	</p>

	<p>
	These entries are not optional and must be informed. Optionally you 
	can configure caching, schema name, query substitutions. You can find more
	information about those on NHibernate documentation.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	Castle ActiveRecord abstracts the configuration from its source using
	the interface <tt>IConfigurationSource</tt>. You can construct an implementation
	yourself if you want to, or you can use one of the three implementations provided, 
	which are listed below.
	</p>
		
	<section id="InPlaceConfigurationSource">
		<title>InPlaceConfigurationSource</title>
		
		<p>
		The <tt>InPlaceConfigurationSource</tt> allows you to hardcode
		the information (or at least part of it) required to configure.
		</p>
		
		<pre format="cs">
using System.Collections;
using Castle.ActiveRecord.Framework.Config;

Hashtable properties = new Hashtable();

properties.Add("connection.driver_class", "NHibernate.Driver.SqlClientDriver");
properties.Add("dialect", "NHibernate.Dialect.MsSql2000Dialect");
properties.Add("connection.provider", "NHibernate.Connection.DriverConnectionProvider");
properties.Add("connection.connection_string", "Data Source=.;Initial Catalog=test;Integrated Security=SSPI");

InPlaceConfigurationSource source = new InPlaceConfigurationSource();

source.Add(typeof(ActiveRecordBase), properties);

ActiveRecordStarter.Initialize(source, typeof(Blog), typeof(Post));</pre>

		<p>
		<tt>InPlaceConfigurationSource</tt> is only recommended in two situations.
		You are getting acquanted with ActiveRecord or your system has a 
		custom configuration support and you want to integrate wit it.
		</p>
	</section>

	<section id="XmlConfigurationSource">
		<title>XmlConfigurationSource</title>
		
		<p>
		You can also read the configuration from a Xml file. 
		The schema is documented on <a href="../manual/xmlconfigref.html">Xml Configuration Reference</a> article.
		</p>

		<pre format="cs">
using Castle.ActiveRecord.Framework.Config;

XmlConfigurationSource config = new XmlConfigurationSource("ARConfig.xml");

ActiveRecordStarter.Initialize(config, typeof(Blog), typeof(Post));</pre>
		
		<warning>
		<p>
		If a non-absolute file is informed like in the example above, 
		the file will be searched based on the working directory. Usually the 
		working directory is the <tt>bin</tt> folder.
		</p>
		</warning>

		<p>
		The <tt>XmlConfigurationSource</tt> is the better approach if you want
		to externalize the configuration in a file with an exclusive purpose
		of holding the ActiveRecord configuration.
		</p>
		
	</section>

	<section id="ActiveRecordSectionHandler">
		<title>ActiveRecordSectionHandler</title>
		
		<p>
		With the <tt>ActiveRecordSectionHandler</tt> you can use the 
		configuration file associated with the <tt>AppDomain</tt>
		(for example the <tt>web.config</tt>).
		The schema is documented on <a href="../manual/xmlconfigref.html">Xml Configuration Reference</a> article.
		</p>
		
		<pre format="cs">
using Castle.ActiveRecord.Framework.Config;

IConfiguration config = ActiveRecordSectionHandler.Instance;

ActiveRecordStarter.Initialize(config, typeof(Blog), typeof(Post));</pre>

		<warning>
		<p>
		If a section is not found an exception will be thrown.
		</p>
		</warning>

	</section>
	
</section>

</body>
</document>
