<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document order="6">
  <properties>
    <title>Castle Project FAQ</title>
  </properties>
<body>

<intro>
<p>
This page has a list of frequently asked questions.
</p>
</intro>

<section id="general">
	<title>General questions</title>

	<section>
		<title>What is Castle Project?</title>
	<p>
	An umbrella for projects that share the same goal: 
	boost productivity while promoting good code and good design.
	For more about it, check our <a href="mission.html">mission</a> and <a href="history.html">history</a>.
	</p>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>How is the community organized?</title>
	<p>
	The project is driven under the light of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meritocracy">meritocracy</a>.
	For more information, check our <a href="../community/index.html">Community</a> area.
	</p>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>I like the project and I'd like to contribute. What should I do?</title>
	<p>
	That's fantastic! We welcome contributions. You can get involved
	with different aspects of the project: from fixing bugs to contributing with better documentation.
	New ideas, features suggestion and constructive criticism are welcome as well.
	For more information, check our <a href="../community/getinvolved.html">Get Involved</a> article.
	</p>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>How can I get professional support?</title>
	<p>
	You have a few options. You can reach <a href="http://www.castlestronghold.com">Castle Stronghold</a>, 
	which sponsors the project and was started 
	by Castle Project's founder. You can also reach committers or advanced users. They might be able to 
	help you as much as Castle Stronghold's team.
	</p>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>What is the Castle Project's license?</title>
	<p>
	The project is release under the terms of Apache Software Foundation License 2.0. Please refer to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apache_license">Apache License</a> for a friendly description.
	</p>
	</section>

</section>

</body>
</document>
